A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 1-3254 FA739A
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 1-3254
1936-2005
1950s-1990s
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA739A
54.72 Cubic Feet Document boxes 1-144.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Catalogued Reports are open for research with select reports restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Other Finding Aids
For descriptions of Ford Foundation Catalogued Reports, please refer to the following finding aids (arranged by Report Number):
FA739B Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 3255-6261
FA739C Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 6262-9286
FA739D Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 9287-11774
FA739E Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 11775-13948
FA739F Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 13949-17726
FA739G Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 17727-19980
Scope and Contents
The Ford Foundation's Catalogued Reports collection includes policy and programming documents, program evaluations, and periodic program status reports produced by Foundation officers and staff, as well as consultants and grantees. Some published material produced by Ford Foundation grants is also included in the collection. The collection also includes some of the Ford Foundation's own publications, such as the Annual Reports and newsletters.
Arrangement
The Catalogued Reports are arranged numerically by an arbitrary call number assigned during cataloging, from 1 to approximately 20,000.
Biographical / Historical
In the early 1970s, the Ford Foundation's archives staff began to identify and catalog individual reports, policy and programming documents, and program evaluations in an effort to create an internal lending-library of useful documents. Many of the Catalogued Reports were physically culled from the former Foundation officers' and staff's archival collections of 'office files'. When those collections of 'office files' were later processed, and finding aids created, an appendix of "Reports Removed" (or, Reports Transferred") was added to the finding aids.
By 1977 the collection included more than 3,500 reports, and by 1979 some 5,000 reports had been cataloged.
Duplicated copies of the reports were also created on microfiche, and later microfilm.
- Graduate studies at the Universidad Central de Venezuela and Instituto Venezolano de Investigaciones Cientificas (Reports 000001), 1963; Busch, Rodolfo H. (Box 1, Reel R-9301)
  Abstract/Summary
  The development of a graduate program at the School of Chemistry of the Central University of Venezuela is proposed. The present situation at the School of Chemistry is examined ... Necessary changes are discussed in detail (Abstract accompanying report)
  Program Name
  Overseas Division/Latin America
  Related Grant Number
  06290324
  Related Grantee Name
  The Ford Foundation
  General Note
  Related Grantee Name: The Ford Foundation
  Curriculum planning -- Venezuela; Science -- Study and teaching -- Venezuela; Universidad Central de Venezuela. Escuela de Química; Instituto Venezolano de Investigaciones Científicas
- Latin America: a preliminary report of development and development possibilities (Reports 000002), 1958; Mintz, Sidney Wilfred, 1922- (Box 1)
  Agriculture -- Latin America -- Research; Economic development projects -- Latin America; Professional education -- Latin America -- Planning; Rural development projects -- Latin America; Community development, Urban -- Latin America
- Report: activities, accomplishments, failures, conclusions, National University of Cordoba (Reports 000003), 1964; Hunter, John M. (John Merlin), 1921- (Box 1)
  The lack of good administration at the university frustrates the development of an institute for sound economic research.
  International Division Latin America and the Caribbean;Latin America and the Caribbean/Argentia and the Southern Cone
  06200031;06290324
  National University Of Cordoba
  Extent
  21 p.
  Ford Foundation Series
  Activities, accomplishments, failures, conclusions, National University of Cordoba
  Economics -- Research -- Argentina; Education -- Argentina; Universidad Nacional de Cordoba
- Secondary agricultural education in Brazil (Reports 000004), 1964; Swanson, Gordon Ira; Kunsela, William R. (Box 1)
  Secondary agricultural education can be improved through teacher training and extending agricultural facilities to secondary schools. Includes statistical tables in Portuguese on the breakdown of professional education in Brazil in the early 1960s.
  International Division Latin America and the Caribbean
  06600193;L64-247
  Federal University Of Parana
  181 p.: maps;28 cm.
  Agriculture -- Study and teaching -- Brazil; Education, Secondary -- Brazil; Agriculture -- Economic aspects -- Brazil; Universidade Federal do Paraná
- Introductory report on Brazilian education with special reference to secondary schools (Reports 000005), 1964; Little, George F. G. (Box 1)
  A concise history of secondary education in Brazil provides an explanatory background to the problems of the five main branches of secondary education in a changing, modern Brazil.
  37 p.
  Education, Secondary -- Brazil
- A study of technical education problems in Brazil (Reports 000006), 1964; Simon, Ernest J., 1893-; French, Albert E.; Adams, H. P. (Henry Packwood); Weekes, Richard V., 1924- (Box 1)
  All Appendices listed in Table of Contents missing from fiche.
  Latin America and the Caribbean/Brazil
  06290324;06500324
  various pagings
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted from scholarly access.
  Engineering -- Study and teaching -- Brazil; Technical education -- Brazil
- Graduate instruction and research in economics in Brazil (Reports 000007), 1963; Schultz, Theodore W. (Theodore William), 1902-1998 (Box 1)
  An expanded program of graduate instruction and research in economics at the University of Sao Paulo, the University of Brazil, and the Vargas Foundation should include micro-and-macro theory, modern statistics and econometrics.
  9 p.
  Economics -- Study and teaching -- Brazil; Universities and colleges -- Graduate work -- Brazil; Universidade de São Paulo; Universidade do Brasil; Fundação Getúlio Vargas
- Ford Foundation mission to Brazil (Reports 000008), 1959; Wolf, Alfred C.; Gordon, Lincoln; Carlson, Reynold E. (Reynold Erland) (Box 1)
  Economic development -- Brazil; Developing countries -- Economic conditions; Education -- Brazil -- Agricultural development projects -- Brazil
- Report of summer consultantship with the Brazil Field Office (Reports 000009), 1964; Baxter, John F. (Box 1)
  Eight areas of science education in Brazil are investigated, 1) Secondary Science Center for the Northeast, University of Recife. 2) Closed Circuit Television Project at the University of Sao Paulo (USP). 3) proposals from the Institute of Chemistry and T
  42 p.
  Related Conference
  National Campaign to Improve High Level Staff.
  Science -- Study and teaching -- Brazil; Universidade Federal do Ceara. Instituto de Quimica e Tecnologia; Universidade Federal de Pernambuco; Instituto Brasileiro de Educação, Ciência e Cultura; Universidade de São Paulo; Pontifícia Universidade Católica do Rio de Janeiro
- Mission report: University of Chile, June 19-July 8 (Reports 000010), 1963; Frodin, Reuben; Morrill, J. L. (James Lewis), 1891-1979 (Box 1)
  Curriculum planning -- Chile; Curriculum evaluation -- Chile; Universidad de Chile
- Ford Foundation Mission to Chile: study of opportunities for support of higher education (Reports 000011), 1961; McConnell, T. R. (Thomas Raymond), 1901-1989; Wickham, Robert S.; Trautman, DeForest L. (Box 1)
  Support should focus on established, nationally supported institutions of higher learning in Chile.
  06190173
  77 p.
  Curriculum planning -- Chile; Universities and colleges -- Administration -- Chile; Universidad de Chile; State Technical University of Chile; Universidad Católica de Valparaíso; Universidad Técnica Federico Santa María; Southern University of Chile
- Recommendations for aid to higher education in Colombia (Reports 000012), 1960; Morrill, J. L. (James Lewis), 1891-1979; Rushton, J. Henry; Frodin, Reuben (Box 2)
  Ways and means of improving their quality and of broadening the educational programs in 14 Colombian universities are discussed.
  Overseas Division/Latin America;Office of the Vice President
  06190002
  27 p.
  Education, Higher -- Colombia
- Education in Colombia: Ford Foundation Mission to Colombia (Reports 000013), 1960; Morse, Richard M. (Richard McGee), 1922-2001; Wickham, Robert S.; Wolf, Alfred C. (Box 2)
  Teacher education, curriculum planning, and educational facilities must be improved to combat illiteracy and the high attrition rate in Colombian Schools.
  47 p.
  Literacy -- Colombia; School facilities -- Colombia; Teachers -- Training of -- Colombia; Educational planning -- Colombia; Colombian Institute for Educational Credit and Technical Studies Abroad
- The organization and administration of the libraries of the National University of Colombia (Reports 000014), 1965; White, Carl Milton, 1903-1983 (Box 2)
  The organization, services, staff and facilities of the National University Library need to be strengthened.
  International Division Latin America and the Caribbean;Office of the Vice President
  06700203;06290324
  National University Of Colombia
  13 p.
  Libraries -- Colombia -- Bogota; Library administration -- Colombia -- Bogota; Academic libraries -- Colombia -- Bogota; Universidad Nacional de Colombia. Biblioteca Central
- Manpower problems and possible policies in Colombia (Reports 000015), 1961; Wellemeyer, J. F. (John Fletcher), 1913- (Box 2)
  Included are: Comments re proposal regarding Colombian manpower studies and Trip notes to Colombia. Data must be gathered to plan an effective manpower development program in Colombia;Cataloged by D.Merkle;Electronic content available in SharePoint Archiv
  82 p.
  Occupational training -- Colombia; Manpower -- Colombia; Colombian Institute for Educational Credit and Technical Studies Abroad; Colombia. Servicio Nacional de Aprendizaje
- A survey of Mexico. (Reports 000016), 1960; Silvert, Kalman H. (Box 2)
  The political, economic and social structures of Mexico are discussed in detail. Historical background on Mexico leading into a discussion of today's educational system.
  141 p.
  Education -- Mexico
- A survey of opportunities for Ford Foundation support to higher education in Peru (Reports 000017), 1962; Hatcher, Harlan; Weber, Ernst; Haviland, H. Field (Henry Field); Wickham, Robert S. (Box 2)
  A broad survey of seven universities in Peru recommends universities for more intensive study with a view to awarding grants.
  L61-1288
  29 p.
  Universities and colleges -- Peru; Education, Higher -- Peru; Universidad Nacional Mayor de San Marcos; La Molina National University of Agriculture; National University of Engineering (Lima, Peru); Pontificia Universidad Católica del Perú; Peruvian University of Medicine and Biology; University of the Pacific
- Report to the Ford Foundation on the National Engineering University, Lima, Peru (Reports 000018), 1963; Low-Maus, Rodolfo; Price, G. Baley (Griffith Baley), 1905-2006; Town, G. A. (George Anthony), 1931- (Box 2)
  The National Engineering University, Lima, Peru, is discussed as to its government, administration, faculty, individual schools, curricula, research, and students. Missing: Conclusion, p. 105+ from both fiche and hard copy.
  Intl Latin America and the Caribbean;Office of the Vice President
  06290324;06590048
  106 p.
  Engineering -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Peru -- Lima; Universidad Nacional de Ingenieria (Peru)
- A study of the academic and administrative organization of the University of the Andes, Merida, Venezuela (Reports 000019), 1963; Elliott, Lloyd H.; Low-Maus, Rodolfo (Box 2)
  The organization and administration of the University of the Andes, Merida, Venezuela were studied. Spanish version included.
  30 p.
  Universities and colleges -- Venezuela -- Administration; Universidad de los Andes (Merida, Venezuela)
- Education in Venezuela (Reports 000020), 1964; Wickham, Robert S. (Box 2)
  A very broad discussion of education, includes a fact sheet on education in Venezuela.
  12 p.
  Education -- Venezuela
- Report of the 1965 Louisiana State University study of the Universidad de Oriente submitted to the Ford Foundation (Reports 000021), Efferson, J. Norman (John Norman), 1912-1990; Sedberry, J. E.; Glenn, John C., 1932- (Box 2)
  An agriculture improvement program should give the field of agronomy top priority.
  L65-618;06290324
  17 p.
  Agriculture -- Research -- Venezuela; Agriculture -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Venezuela; Universidad de Oriente (Cumaná, Venezuela)
- Survey and recommendations for the libraries of the Universidad de Oriente (Reports 000022), 1963; Milczewski, Marion A. (Marion Anthony), 1912-1981 (Box 2)
  The need for marked improvement in organization, collections, personnel, services, and use of libraries of the University of Oriente, Venezuela, in teaching and research is discussed. Page 9 missing from both fiche and hard copy.
  Latin America and the Caribbean;Office of the Vice President
  Academic libraries -- Venezuela -- Administration; Universidad de Oriente (Cumaná, Venezuela). Biblioteca General
- Recommendations to Ford Foundation for support of economic research programs in Brazil (Reports 000023), 1959; Neal, Alfred Clarence; Carlson, Reynold E. (Reynold Erland) (Box 2)
  Studies on economic statistics, prices, family budget, national accounts project, fiscal project, and agricultural economics are better conducted by the Vargas Foundation than by the universities.
  06000470
  Getulio Vargas Foundation
  24 p.
  Economics -- Research -- Brazil; Fundação Getúlio Vargas
- A study of opportunities for a Ford Foundation program in Venezuela (Reports 000024), 1962; Hatcher, Harlan; Weber, Ernst; Haviland, H. Field (Henry Field); Wickham, Robert S. (Box 2)
  A general discussion of education leads to specific funding proposals for social science and engineering studies.
  57 p.
  Universities and colleges -- Venezuela; Social sciences -- Venezuela; Social sciences -- Study and teaching -- Venezuela; Education, Higher -- Venezuela; Engineering -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Venezuela; Economics -- Study and teaching -- Venezuela; Universidad de los Andes (Bogotá, Colombia); Universidad Católica Andrés Bello; Universidad Central de Venezuela; Universidad de Oriente (Cumaná, Venezuela); Center for Development Studies
- Manpower survey prepared for the Instituto Torcuato Di Tella (Reports 000025), 1961; Thomas, Robert L., 1928- (Box 2)
  This manpower survey is a blueprint for determining the demand-supply situation for technicians, professionals, and administrative management personnel.
  International Division Latin America and the Caribbean;Office of the Vice President;Latin America and the Caribbean/Argentia and the Southern Cone
  06190327;06090238
  35 p.
  Personnel management -- Argentina; Occupational surveys -- Argentina
- Economics in Argentina: A report based on a consulting assignment (Reports 000026), 1965; Carmichael, William D. (William Daniel), 1929-; Grunwald, Joseph, 1920- (Box 2)
  Progress is reported and evaluated for 8 grants related to economics.
  International Division Latin America and the Caribbean;Latin America and the Caribbean/Argentia and the Southern Cone;Office of the Vice President
  06200026;06200031;06200235;06300114;PA63-381;A63-548;06490004;0650087;06290324
  25 p.
  Economics -- Research -- Argentina; Subsidies -- Argentina; Economics -- Study and teaching -- Argentina; Scholarships -- Argentina; Universidad de Buenos Aires; Universidad Nacional de Cordoba; Universidad Nacional de Tucumán; Instituto Torcuato Di Tella; Fundación de Investigaciones Económicas Latinoamericanas (Buenos Aires, Argentina); Instituto para el Desarrollo de Ejecutivos en la Argentina
- Ford Foundation mission to Argentina (Reports 000027), 1959; Wolf, Alfred C.; Silvert, Kalman H.; Carlson, Reynold E. (Reynold Erland) (Box 2)
  Funding proposals include atomic energy research for peace time, university improvement, economic research, and public administration studies.
  28 p.
  Public administration -- Argentina; Economics -- Research -- Argentina; Education, Higher -- Argentina; Universidad de Buenos Aires; Instituto de Investigaciones de Productos Naturales de Análisis y de Síntesis Orgánica (Argentina)
- Report on visit to Chile and Argentina, July 15-August 25 (Reports 000028), 1962; Baxter, John F. (Box 2)
  Brief notes and recommendations are presented of a series of conferences, discussions and meetings held on the use of educational television for basic science instruction at the secondary and university levels.
  Television in education -- Chile; Television in education -- Argentina
- A report of a survey of vocational and technical education in Chile (Reports 000029), 1963; Butler, John A.; Jeppsen, Ernest C., 1903-; Rao, K. Nagaraja (Krishnappa Nagaraja), 1921- (Box 2)
  Manpower needs in Chile can be filled by an improved, extensive program of technical and vocational education.
  06390295;L68-90.
  83 p.
  Survey of vocational and technical education in Chile
  Occupational training -- Chile; Technical education -- Chile; Vocational education -- Chile; Universidad Técnica Federico Santa María; State Technical University of Chile
- The educational system and applied social research in Argentina (Reports 000030), 1959; Street, James H. (James Howell), 1903-1954 (Box 3, Reel R-9301)
  A broad view of education concludes there is little serious social and economic research going on in Argentina.
  L57-531
  Social sciences -- Argentina; Education -- Argentina
- University education in Central America (Reports 000031), 1962; Enarson, Harold L., 1919-2006 (Box 3)
  All aspects of university education are reviewed with the conclusion that the universities would benefit by regional cooperation.
  International Division Latin America and the Caribbean;Office of the Vice President;Latin America and the Caribbean/Mexico and Central America
  06290148;06200109
  Higher Council of Central American Universities
  97 p.
  Universities and colleges -- Central America; Education, Higher -- Central America; University cooperation -- Central America; Consejo Superior Universitario Centroamericano; Universidad de Costa Rica; Universidad Nacional Autónoma de Honduras; Universidad de El Salvador; Universidad de San Carlos de Guatemala
- Mexico: Ford Foundation science and engineering initial program report (Reports 000032), 1965; Rice, Harold S. (Box 3)
  Rapid industrial growth in Mexico demands an increase in scientific manpower.
  Science & Engineering
  Occupational training -- Mexico; Science -- Study and teaching -- Mexico; Engineering--Study and teaching -- Mexico
- Educational television (ETV) in Colombia (Reports 000033), 1963; Mitchell, Clifton; Armsey, James W., 1917-2008; Fraenkel, Peter Adolf, 1923-2007 (Box 3)
  A proposal by the Government of Colombia to the United States for assistance by the Peace Corps and AID in the development and use of educational television is assessed from a Foundation viewpoint.
  L62-1104
  15 p. plus attachments.
  Television in education -- Colombia; Ford Foundation. Overseas Development Program
- Proposal for a center for teacher training and curriculum development: memorandum (Reports 000034), 1965; Shaplin, Judson T. (Box 3)
  Support to a center for the development of secondary school teachers and curriculum is recommended.
  06500329
  Institute Of International Education, Inc.
  11 p.
  Teachers -- Training of -- Chile; High school teachers -- Chile; Institute of International Education (New York, N.Y.)
- Economics teaching and training of economists in Brazil: An appraisal with recommendations (Reports 000035), 1961; Hagen, Everett Einar; Nicholls, William Hord, 1914- (Box 3)
  A center for graduate studies in economics should be founded in Rio de Janeiro.
  International Division Latin America and the Caribbean;Office of the Vice President;Latin America and the Caribbean/Brazil
  06090201
  62 p.
  Economics -- Study and teaching (Graduate) -- Brazil; Universities and colleges -- Brazil -- Graduate work; Fundação Getúlio Vargas; Universidade de São Paulo; Universidade do Brasil; Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais; Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul
- Report of the Ford Foundation mission to Mexico (Reports 000036), 1961; Millett, John; Howe, W. H. (Walter Henry), 1848-; Mintz, Sidney Wilfred, 1922-; Tierney, James F. (Box 3)
  A sampling of the major Mexican institutes of higher learning provides general impressions of Mexican education, sociology, and political scene, as well as specific funding proposals.
  L61-1111
  116 p.
  Education, Higher -- Mexico; Universities and colleges -- Mexico
- La Escuela Nacional de Bibliotecarios y Archivistas (Reports 000037), 1965; White, Carl Milton, 1903-1983 (Box 3)
  The importance of the library function in a developing Mexico cannot be overestimated. Books and buildings, but most of all, manpower, are important in library development.
  L66-37;06290324;06790023.
  Library planning -- Mexico; Library science -- Mexico; Library employees -- Mexico; National School of Librarians and Archivists.
- The social sciences in Mexico: report on a visit (Reports 000038), 1963; Mintz, Sidney Wilfred, 1922- (Box 3)
  Educational development in the social sciences should be concentrated on the two institutions where efforts are most likely to bring rewards.
  06290136
  89 p.
  Education, Higher -- Mexico; Sociology -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Mexico; Anthropology -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Mexico; Social sciences -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Mexico; National School of Veracruz; Escuela Nacional de Antropología e Historia (Mexico)
- Mexico population program (Reports 000039), 1965; Trowbridge, James W. (Box 3)
  Rapid population growth can frustrate Mexico's goals of advanced development. National awareness of the need for growth control is needed.
  Birth control -- Mexico
- A report of a survey of industrial and technical education in Argentina (Reports 000041), 1963; Butler, John A.; Jeppsen, Ernest C., 1903-; Rao, K. Nagaraja (Krishnappa Nagaraja), 1921- (Box 3)
  A collaboration between CONET and Ford Foundation is proposed to establish two vocational teacher training centers.
  06390295
  99 p.
  Educational planning -- Argentina; Manual training -- Argentina; Technical education -- Argentina; Vocational teachers -- Argentina; Teachers -- Training of -- Argentina; Vocational education -- Argentina; Consejo Nacional de Educación Técnica (Argentina)
- Justification and preliminary proposal of a Ford Foundation grant in demography and population studies in Colombia (Reports 000042), 1964; Zschock, Dieter K. (Box 3)
  A "Committee for the Scientific Study of Population" under the auspices of the Association of Medical Faculties will coordinate teaching and research efforts by medical faculties and will include social scientists at all levels of teaching.
  06500111;L64-926
  Colombian Association of Faculties of Medicine
  39 p.
  Demography -- Colombia; Birth control -- Colombia; Colombian Association of Faculties of Medicine.